"Tackling the Root Cause of Obesity
Without Drugs Like Ozempic"
Introducing a temporary
weight-loss fix
using GLP-1 drugs like Ozempic,
without consideration
of their wider implications
and a long-term plan,
has been likened to sprinkling
water on a raging blaze.
The war against obesity
cannot be won without measures
to prevent obesity
in the first place.
That means tackling
the food environment,
which is based on high-calorie,
fatty, salty, sugary junk,
rather than relying
on medication
as a "damage limitation
exercise."
Yeah, but limiting damage
is a good thing.
Sure, these drugs may not make
much of a dent
on a population scale,
but what about
on an individual basis?
It’d be great if people ate
healthfully enough
to prevent and treat
heart disease,
high blood pressure,
and diabetes too,
but until that happens,
drugs for those conditions
can literally be life saving.
Obesity so dramatically
decreases one’s lifespan--
reducing life expectancy
as much as a decade--
that these GLP-1 drugs--
like bariatric surgery--
should be considered
as a last resort
for those unwilling
or unable to treat
the cause of their obesity.
Put diabetics on Ozempic,
and they eat less
high-fat and sweet foods.
Put nondiabetics on Ozempic,
and they eat less high-fat
and non-sweet foods.
So, diabetics on Ozempic
are eating fewer
pastries and doughnuts,
and nondiabetics on Ozempic
are eating fewer ham, cheese,
and sausage sandwiches.
The problem
is people eat too much crap;
so, anything that gets people
to eat less crap
can be beneficial,
including surgically rearranging
our digestive organs
with bariatric surgery.
But we don’t need
to go under the knife
or take a $1,000-a-month drug
to de-crap our diet.
But what about the cravings,
though?
The obesogenic environment--
that is, the obesity-generating
toxic food environment--
can overwhelm
even substantial efforts
to enact individual
behavioral changes.
After ramping up for three
months to high-dose Ozempic,
people are able
to cut nearly 1,000 calories
out of their daily diet.
How could you possibly do that
without drugs,
unless you were on some kind
of liquid diet
meal-replacement shakes
or something?
Or, you could eat
a diet centered around
the healthiest foods
on the planet.
If you put people on a diet
packed with fruits, vegetables,
whole grains, and beans,
and allow them to eat
as much as they want,
they end up eating about
50 percent fewer calories
than they might have otherwise.
Just as full,
on half the calories.
Wait. How can people be
satisfied after cutting
more than 1,000 calories
out of their daily diets?
By eating more high-bulk,
low-calorie-density foods
(vegetables, fruits,
whole grains, and beans)
and fewer calorie-dense foods,
like meats, cheeses,
sugars, and fats.
No wonder a whole food
plant-based diet apparently
achieved greater weight loss
than any other diet.
So, could good nutrition present
a safer and cheaper approach
to weight loss
for most patients?
Not only can the ingestion
of a plant-based meal
more than double
GLP-1 secretion,
compared to
a same-calorie meat meal,
but plant-based diets
can also cause weight loss
by virtue of calorie-trapping,
high-fiber foods,
which flush calories away,
or by boosting
our resting metabolic rate,
which helps explain
why the largest study
of vegans to date
showed that those eating
strictly plant-based diets
are about 35 pounds (16 kg)
lighter, on average.
One randomized trial found
that a strictly plant-based diet
may reduce annual food costs
by about $500.
Healthier, more plant-based,
diets may be about
25 percent less expensive.
And eating groats and greens,
maybe even spicy
groats and greens,
may be able to provide
an extra GLP-1 boost.
For more healthy
weight-loss tips,
check out my evidence-based
weight-loss book,
for which all proceeds I receive
are donated to charity.
The Drug and Therapeutics
Bulletin,
which is also independent
and doesn’t accept
any advertising,
concluded that more data
on Ozempic’s
long-term safety and efficacy
are needed
before it can be recommended
for routine use
for the treatment of obesity,
reminding readers
that historically,
nearly all the drugs
approved for weight loss
have later been
pulled from the market
because of safety concerns.
But wait.
Obesity so dramatically
decreases one’s lifespan
that even if these drugs
ended up shaving years
off of people’s lives,
wouldn’t they still be worth it?
Well, that assumes
these drugs cure obesity,
but if you remember from
the drug’s own package insert,
in all the major trials,
people started out obese
and ended up obese,
after the drugs effectively
stopped working
and body weight plateaus.
Then, you’re paying to take the
drug for the rest of your life
just so you don’t lose ground
and re-gain everything,
while continuing to face any
and all long-term side effects.
Historically, the medical
profession has offered
a sorry collection of harmful
or downright dangerous
weight-loss interventions.
Caution about
long-term side effects is,
therefore, warranted.
If you look at
the post-approval withdrawal
of anti-obesity drugs,
pulled from the market
because of safety concerns
only discovered years later,
it took an average of a decade
before dangers came to light,
and in one case,
we didn’t discover
a weight-loss drug’s
long-term adverse effects
until 38 years
after it hit the market.
What’s more, even after
that first report of danger,
it takes an average
of another decade
to actually get it banned.
It can even take as long as
another two decades,
even though people died
in about a quarter of cases.
As one critic said about how
long it takes regulators to act:
"It would probably
take the system 2 years
to ban cyanide.”
Just recently,
a French drug maker was fined
nearly half a billion dollars
for fraudulently
and relentlessly promoting
its appetite-suppressing
weight-loss drug
while covering up known harms,
causing hundreds or thousands to
die from heart valve problems.
At least it learned its lesson,
though.
I mean, what other drug company
would conceal the harms
of appetite suppressors
after a fine that big?
After all, it was only making up
to 20 million euros a year.
Let me do the math real quick...
That’ll teach ’em!
These days, GLP-1 drug makers
are worth more
than a trillion dollars.
I’m sure they would never try
to cover anything up.